I hear from lots of
people every day
who are concerned about how
their diet is affecting their health.
They need answers
based on facts.
In other words,
in the peer-reviewed
medical literature,
and that is what
I’m here for.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
If you think the claim of
‘younger looking skin overnight’
sounds a bit too good to be true,
you may be right.
Today is the first in our two-part series
on the efficacy of anti-aging creams.
What is the truth about
over-the-counter “anti-aging” products,
which constitute
a billion-dollar industry.
There is a “psychological effect
from spending more,”
wrote a team of dermatologists,
but “don’t be seduced by fancy
packaging and high prices.”
Many products advertise dramatic results
that are frequently exaggerated
and misleading and are rarely
scientifically supported.
An independent product testing
institute questioned the efficacy
of anti-aging creams generally,
find that beneficial effects
could only be picked up
using sensitive instruments
without becoming clinically
or noticeably detectable.
They suggest these products may not work
any better than typical moisturizers.
Cross-sectional studies
of Chinese and British women found
that those who regularly
used facial moisturizers
were guessed to be about
two years younger
than those the same age who didn’t.
However, a third, larger Dutch study
did not, and regardless,
snapshot-in-time studies can
never establish cause-and-effect.
Studies on moisturizers are limited.
But they can improve
the appearance of dry skin,
which can otherwise look discolored,
flaky, and rough.
Moisturizers can hydrate the skin
and may reduce the appearance of fine lines
by 15 to 20%, called “the oldest trick
[in] the cosmetic industry,”
but may not do anything
to treat the underlying cause.
Whether facial foundation,
or night cream, or anti-aging serum,
the formulations of most skin products
are basically a moisturizer
combined with purported active
ingredients for marketing appeal.
Which ingredients are actually
active anti-aging agents?
I’ll give you hint:
Up to 90% of the visible aging of
someone’s face is due to sun exposure.
From an anti-aging standpoint,
the most biologically active ingredient
in skin products is sunscreen.
Considered the most important thing
to maintaining youthful skin
is the daily application of sunscreen
and other protective measures
like wearing a hat.
All other things you can do
for your skin pale in comparison,
especially for those
with pale skin.
To prevent skin cancer,
the American Academy of Dermatology
recommends sunscreen
with an SPF of 30 or higher,
but an SPF of 15
can prevent skin aging.
How do we know?
Because it’s been put to the test.
Nine hundred adults were randomized
to years of daily sunscreen use
or to continue with their own
discretionary use.
(It was considered unethical
to withhold protection
by giving people placebo sunscreen.)
In the end, 77% in the recommended
daily sunscreen group
were applying sunscreen at least
three to four days per week
compared with 33% in the
discretionary use group.
Would that be enough
of a difference to make a difference?
Yes, there was significantly less skin
aging in the instructed daily use group.
In fact, they suffered no
detectable increase in skin aging
over the 4.5-year study.
The researchers concluded,
“Daily sunscreen use protects
against skin aging.”
Although sunscreens are primarily
intended to prevent further facial aging
rather than reverse
photodamage already done,
some in the daily sunscreen use group
did show an improvement in skin texture.
The results are all the more striking
given the control group was told
to continue to use sunscreen and hats
whenever they thought necessary,
suggesting people are poor judges
or planners for excess UV exposure
when left to their own devices.
So, a daily facial moisturizer
with an SPF 15 in it
is recommended, even if it’s cloudy
or raining outside.
Considered the “gold standard”
for anti-aging skin care:
“daily use of sunscreens in the
daytime and retinoids at night.”
Retinoids?
I’ll cover them next.
Sunscreens are intended to prevent
further facial photoaging
but can’t dramatically reverse
damage presently visible,
whereas topical retinoids
are the most important drug class
to reverse the signs of aging.
Also known as all-trans
retinoic acid, tretinoin
(sold under a variety
of brands including Retin-A)
is a prescription-only
topical form of vitamin A
that can visibly improve mild
to moderate photodamage,
including fine and coarse wrinkles,
freckles, other pigmentation,
and improve overall skin texture
after months of daily use.
This is accompanied by
a restoration of collagen formation.
Skin biopsies taken before
and after 10 to 12 months
of tretinoin versus placebo
found that while skin collagen formation
dropped 14% in the control group,
it rose 80% in the retinoic acid group.
The downsides are the side-effects,
so common they have their own name—
“retinoid reaction”—plaguing
a high proportion of patients,
including redness, stinging,
burning, itching, and peeling.
Ironically, the constant irritation
may be a causal mechanism,
constantly forcing the skin to renew.
The adverse effects do
tend to improve over time
after a peak after about
two weeks of daily use.
And you can minimize the irritation
by starting at a lower concentration
(for example .025% instead of 0.1%)
and slowly ramping up from applying
at first twice a week for a few weeks,
then to every other night
for a few more weeks
before finally advancing
to nightly application as tolerated.
Given that a small amount
is systemically absorbed,
out of an abundance of caution
women of child-bearing capacity
may want steer clear,
given the severe birth defects
caused by a similar drug,
isotretinoin
(sold formerly
as the acne drug Accutane).
There are gentler, less potent,
over-the-counter topical retinoids:
retinyl, retinol, and retinal.
There’s retinyl acetate,
retinyl palmitate,
retinyl propionate, retinol,
and retinaldehyde.
Once absorbed into your skin,
your body can convert them
into small amounts of retinoic acid.
However, data is limited on these
nonprescription retinoids.
The results of clinical trials
on the retinyl esters
have been routinely disappointing.
Even 48 weeks of daily use
was found to be ineffective
for reducing wrinkles
compared to placebo.
Retinaldehyde and retinol,
however, hold some promise.
There was a 48-week
head-to-head trial
of retinaldehyde vs.
retinoic acid vs. placebo.
Now retinoids can be so irritating
that it’s hard to blind participants
as to whether or not
they’re in the control group;
so, objective measures that may be
less susceptible to placebo effects
are especially important.
So, what they did
is make silicone molds
of the crow’s feet wrinkles
around the eyes of the participants
before and after being randomized
to one of those three groups,
and then analyzed scans
of the molds
using high-resolution
digital image processing.
The retinaldehyde group
showed a similar reduction
in fine lines and wrinkles as the
retinoic acid group with less irritation.
Only 23% of the retinaldehyde group
experienced skin irritation,
compared to 71% in the retinoic acid group,
versus 4% in the placebo cream group.
Of all the nonprescription
retinoid options,
retinol may be the preferred choice, though.
It causes even less irritation
than retinaldehyde
(insignificantly different than placebo),
and a randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
found that 52 weeks of use
improved crow’s feet fine lines
by 44% and mottled pigmentation by 84%.
But tretinoin—retinoic acid—has by far
the most robust track record of efficacy;
so, why not just ask
your doctor for a prescription?
Because long-term topical tretinoin
use may increase your risk
of an even more
stinging side-effect: death.
Topical Tretinoin Therapy
and All-Cause Mortality:
The Veterans Affairs Topical
Tretinoin Chemoprevention trial
was to be a six-year randomized
controlled trial to see
if it could help
prevent skin cancer.
But the trial had to be stopped early
because significantly more people
were dying in the retinoic acid group
than in the placebo-cream group.
At the time the study was halted,
19% of the subjects
in the tretinoin group had died,
compared to 14% in the placebo group.
Between 1 to 8%
of topically applied retinoic acid
is absorbed into the bloodstream.
Could it be killing people?
We don’t know if the increase
in deaths was a statistical fluke
that happened by chance
or a real biological effect.
The probability that we’d see
such a discrepancy just by chance
is about 1 in a 100.
Tretinoin continues to be banned
in Europe for cosmetic purposes.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
premiering at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.